Uh, next up we have Neil's R, uh, who is
a machine learning engineer at
HuggingFace. Um, who uses who who is
absolutely infatuated by open-source
software um, libraries and things like
that? Everyone love open source. Who
cares as much? Two hands. That's a
that's a proper open source. Who cares
as much about open- source models?
Okay, pretty much the same. It's
interesting. I always see like so much
love for open source software, but then
actually when the models come, we tend
to jump much much more for the
anthropics or the open AIs because, you
know, they're far more performant and
things like that. But we, you know, open
source models have come such a long way
even in the very very short term. and
Neils is gonna talk us through this and
talk us about where open source models
are today and whether or not we should
be using them. So, please give it up for
Neils Re.
[music]
All right. Thanks a lot uh Devcon for
having me here. So today I'm going to be
talking a bit about the state of open
source AM models for coding.
Quick introduction. So I'm Neils. I'm
coming from uh Belgium, the land of
fries, beer, chocolate. Um I do work uh
yeah at Hacking Face. I also do work
actually as a consultant uh at ML6 in
Belgium. And I love contributing to open
source uh and loving giving tutorials to
to people. Um so in today's talk I'm
just going to give a brief introduction
to hugging phase and the hugging face
ecosystem. Uh and then let's talk about
the rise of all of these openly
available large language models and a
lot of them are being used for coding
purposes.
So in case you don't know what hugging
phase is uh our co likes to call it the
github of uh machine learning. So GitHub
yeah you can host code on there uh
typically small small files few
kilobytes to a few megabytes but once
you want to host machine learning models
or huge machine learning data sets um
yeah GitHub is not really the place for
that. Uh so hacking phase platform this
is like the feed you see when you go to
uh hugging face um yeah basically gives
you access to a huge range of openly
available machine learning models and
data sets. Currently, we have more than
2 million publicly available AI models
from all kinds of labs, including
OpenAI, uh, including other labs like
Deepseek and so on. We have more than
500,000 data sets now available on the
Hegnace website. All available for free.
And on the left sidebar, you can easily
filter on a domain that you care about.
Could be computer vision model. It could
be large language model. It could be an
speech recognition model like Whisper,
for example. There are tons of use cases
available on hugging face.
So in terms of the ecosystem, I would
say the hugging face hub is really the
central place. If you come to
huggingface.com, uh you will you will
find it there. Uh so as I said, huge
range of openly available data sets and
models are available there and then you
can start playing around with these
using one of our open- source uh
libraries like the transformers library
is one of our most popular uh open
source libraries. We have more than
150,000 GitHub stars there. Diffusers is
more used for yeah diffusion based
models. We have a ton more open source
models like TRL which allows you to
fine-tune open source LMS and so on. Um
and then yeah you can either create a
demo for your model uh through what we
call hacking face spaces which is
basically a hosted environment for
streamlit grado or just uh a plain
docker image. Um so you can create a
fancy demo there to showcase what your
model is capable of and if you want to
deploy it um we offer some solutions
there as well. Uh we have serverless
inference using inference endpoints
which is very similar to the open AI
API. Uh we also have inference providers
which is for um dedicated inference
where the model is only running for you.
U but you can actually as it's open
source you can just download a model
from hacking face and deploy it anywhere
you want. You can deploy it on Google
cloud, you can deploy it on your own
data center, you can deploy it on a
phone uh wherever you want.
So actually the transformers library
which is still the most popular library
built by hanging face uh was born in
2018 when Google open sourced birds soon
after the original transformer. Um and
then yeah we really had a boom of a huge
range of models being released um on
hugging face. So and today yeah we have
a lot of open openly available large
language models from companies like
Meta, Google, uh Mistrol but also a lot
of Chinese upcoming players like
Moonshot uh and so on. Now u a lot of
people use the term open source but
actually it's often times just open
weights. So there's a big difference
between closed source models then you
have open weight models and then you
have fully open source models. So yeah,
for example, Gemini 3 which just came
out, that's an example of a proprietary
model or closed source. We don't know
anything about it. Well, we know it's
some transformer being trained using an
auto reggressive uh task, but we don't
know which training data was used to to
make it. Um there's not a lot of details
available. Um and then you have the open
weight model. So a lot of these trending
models on hugging phase are actually
open weight, which means that the
weights are available on hugging face.
uh but we don't know the training data
that was used to create these models. We
don't know the exact training objectives
that were used. The code was not uh made
available. So examples of that include
the Quen models from Alibaba. Uh the
Mistro models, Deepseek for example also
released models on Hugging Phase but
these are open weights
uh because the training code was not
released and the training data was also
not released. And then on the other side
of the spectrum we have the fully open
source models. Um so their hugging face
has some initiatives like the small LM
series which are yeah smaller models
that you can run on device let's say on
your phone or laptop. Uh and there are
other initiatives like Almo from Alen AI
which is an institute in Seattle and
there you have full access not just to
the weights but also to the entire
training data set and the code used to
train uh the model.
So yeah, it's a bit of a trade-off
between open source versus
proprietaries. Uh they each have their
advantages and their disadvantages. Uh
one big big advantage of an closed
source model is just performance is
typically uh really good out of the box.
You can just use it out of the box and
it will work quite well. Uh but of
course it comes with some disadvantages
as well because you're like quite
dependent on another party. Um you
cannot really easily customize the
model. Um whereas in an open source
model yeah the model is only running for
you. So you have much more control over
it. Also in terms of latency for example
it will be much lower. Uh you can
customize it. You can fine-tune it uh on
your own data sets to make it really
good at your own uh domain. Um but of
course there's a bit of a learning curve
there. Uh it's not that easy to just
fine-tune an LM and also deploy it. Um,
so each have their their pros and cons,
but what is very interesting to me is
that the gap terms of performance
between open and closed source is
closing over time. Like when we were in
2023, open air was releasing GP4 and at
the time we didn't really have any good
openly available models. Then Mistral 7B
for example came out. Um but still the
gap was quite large and now um yeah
we're now in 2025 and this gap has
really become uh very very small. Uh we
see very strong models coming out
especially from Chinese players. Um yeah
that make it basically on par with the
with the closed source models and this
is also an interesting trend uh the fact
that China is like taking over in terms
of hugging face down on yeah on the
hugging face website. So previously we
had like the Llama series from Meta
which were very popular and lots of use
cases were built on top of them but for
example Llama 4 was not really big big
success. Um and we really saw a flip
happening this year where um yeah
companies like Alibaba with their very
strong Quen models, Deepseek which came
in the news and now it's Moonshot which
is having the strongest models. Yeah
they really took over in terms of best
openly available uh models.
You might wonder uh why would you uh
fine-tune
um a model? So here I have some examples
like cursor actually they also are
building on top of openly available
models from hacking face for example to
make it really strong on a custom task
on a custom domain in this case is their
top completion model. Uh this is
actually some open source models. They
took some very strong pre-trained base
model from hugging face and then they
made it really good at uh yeah
predicting what you might write next in
your IDE. Um so they are using an open
source model behind the scenes. Uh
another example of this is the composer
model that cursor is now using. Uh yeah,
I suspect they are using one of these
Chinese models as the base as the
foundation of composer and then they
fine-tune it using reinforcement
learning techniques. Uh and this is not
just to make it very strong within
cursor uh to be a coding agent but also
for latency purposes because like a big
frustration of mine was also when I use
set for example in cursor it can be very
slow. I'm just waiting for the coding
agent to to complete. Composer is much
faster and it actually is mostly on par
with it. So that's another reason. Um
also yeah for semantic search it's
actually really good. So this is really
for the custom domain reason why you
want to find tune model. It's it's
outperforming the closed source models
because it has been trained within the
cursor environment.
Um yeah another example here is wind
surf cognition. They also took one of
these Chinese models. Uh in this case
they took GLM 4.6 six which is one of
the best openly available LLMs today on
hacking phase and then they did some
reinforcement learning training on top
of that and then they use cerebras which
is like an inference provider that yeah
they create custom chips to make LMS run
really really fast. So this allows them
yeah to have much much lower latency
compared to the closed source models. A
final example is uh an example I saw on
Twitter from data do. They also uh
replaced their closed source uh models.
They were using openi before uh by fine-
tuning on top of llama mainly also for
latency reasons like they required less
than 500 milliseconds of latency um
which apparently was not really uh
doable with a clusters model. So this
might be another reason why and also
apparently for cost reasons it can be
yeah especially if your data volume is
really high uh these closed source
models you are paying per 1 million
input and output tokens but if you have
a huge data volume then it might become
cheaper to just use in an open source
model.
All right and yeah I actually took a
look at like all of the openly available
coding models that were released on
hugging face over the last few years. Uh
yeah, of course it's not an exhaustive
list. I had to skip some. I just
included some that I think were uh were
worth mentioning. Uh but it actually
started in September 2022 uh when
hacking face started the big code
initiative. I have a slide on that and
today we have like Kim K2 a Chinese
model uh which is really great at
coding. So yeah, this is just another
remark like all of these uh great coding
models are all Chinese uh nowadays.
So yeah uh for some brief history in
2023 or 2022 I think uh hugging face
started the big code initiative where
like thousands of people were involved.
The goal was at that time GitHub copilot
was the strongest coding agent. it was
more like just an autocomplete on
steroids u you could use and the goal
was to create something similar but make
it openly available for everyone. So
this is really also the mission of
hacking face not just open source but
also open science really sharing uh the
knowledge so that people can build on
top of each other's work and the first
uh release that came out of this big
code initiative is star coder uh at the
time so this was a 50 billion parameter
model trained on 80 different
programming languages and it had this
huge context window of just 8k tokens
um and this was just the f uh the first
release so interestingly they used this
pre-training objective called FIM or
fill in fill in the middle which is
actually from a paper from uh openAI. So
the idea is actually pretty simple. Uh
so let's say you have this piece of code
you just provide uh the first block of
code as well as the last block of code
to the model and it needs to predict
what's in the middle. Uh and this allows
you to create um these step completion
models. Um and I think nowadays uh these
models are still being pre-trained using
this fill-in-the-middle objective
alongside the model. Uh of course as
hugging phase is fully open. So it's not
just about the weights, it's also about
the code and the training data. Uh
hugging phase released what is called
the stack which is the huge data set
that was used to train star coder. So
this was 3 terabytes of fully uh
permissively licensed source code all
sourced from GitHub and the whole
pipeline used to create that data set
including like filtering because you
need to filter for example out
lowquality code and so on it was all
made available alongside a research
paper so that people can uh yeah build
on top of this. Then a year later in
2024 um hugging phase released star
coder 2 which build on top of this. Uh
now the models came in three sizes from
3 billion to 15 billion and they also
reached a new uh larger training data
set called the stack v2. Um so this was
trained on 4 trillion tokens and the
context window increased. Um so in total
yeah 900 billion uh unique tokens were
made available. Uh and this was much
more than just uh code
but if you look at the benchmarks at the
time like Deepseek coder was probably
the best model out there. um they
compared here and they said that in the
50 billion range uh star coder 2 was
like among the best available models but
this is still 2024. If we then uh look
forward to uh end of 2024 uh Quen
started to pop up. So Quen is an AI lab
from Alibaba. Um so they released Quen
2.5 coder which at the time was the new
state-of-the-art for open weights
coding. So here they are already
starting to compare against cloth 3.5
sonet which was the best model at the
time. It came in different sizes from
0.5 billion all the way up to 32
billion.
Um yeah unfortunately I don't have the
time to go into all the details but they
actually also released a paper on
hugging face detailing how they create
this model. So it's they do file level
pre-training repo level pre-training and
then a whole post- training phase using
synthetic data and so on. Uh so I
recommend reading the paper if you're
interested in that. Um and then people
as uh Quen Reese's modelace people can
start building on top of this. Um so for
example here Z which is this opensource
IDE um they fine- tuned Quen 2.5 uh for
the task of next edit prediction uh tab
completion. Um and so this model was
also made available on hacking phase
they call it Zetta and they did not just
raise the model but also the data set
used to train this and it's actually
being used in production inside their
AD. Another example is fast apply which
is an apply model. So it will take in
the code that the coding agent generates
and then it needs to figure out given
the current state of the files where
does it need to apply those changes. So
this was also a fine tune of quen 2.5.
Then in 2025 there was Deepseek R1. Uh
yeah this really was the first time that
an open source model made it into the
news like mainstream uh because yeah it
had some impact on the stock of Nvidia
on the on the value of of Nvidia. Um but
again it's an open weights model. So
yeah there was uh a technical report. So
the whole technique behind it is called
RLVR or reinforcement learning from
verifiable rewards. And this is what all
the top AI labs are currently doing.
They're all scaling this RLVR uh
process.
So yeah, if you want to learn more about
what RLVR is, there's a great tech
report from Lenai on on that.
But as it's not fully open source, so
it's only the weights that Deepseek
released on Hacking Face, Hacking Face
uh released open R1 which is a fully
open source reproduction of the Deepseek
R1 uh model. So including the training
data including the whole code and the
whole process to create such a deepse R1
uh model it's available on GitHub as
well and then this here we have uh the
successor of Quen 2.5 which is Quen 3 uh
coder well there's quen 3 which is which
are the LLMs and then there are some
models which um are trained further on
top of that for coding purposes um so in
this case they switch to a mixture of
experts architectures or IMO ES and
they're pretty large. So 480 billion
parameters with 35 billion active per
token and so on. Uh sadly they only
reached the instruction tuned versions
not the base versions. There is also no
paper. Um but it still allows people uh
to build on top of them. So this is
another uh Chinese model that was also
released soon after Quen 3 coder. Uh
these models are called are
[clears throat] called GLM. uh there's
GLM 4.5 and then uh 4.6 has also been
released. These are also adopting the
mixture of experts architecture and
they're also pretty large 355 billion
parameters in total. Um and as you can
see they they compare against like the
strongest uh closed source models out
there including open 03 or clot for opus
for example uh and they raise them in
both a thinking version and a
non-thinking uh version. Yeah, I don't
have the details to go into the how they
created this model, but there is a paper
available. So, you can also see like how
how they do the pre-training, how they
do the mid training, which is a stage
between the pre-training and the post
training. Um and again they use this FIM
or fill in the middle objective uh to
train on on code
and they even open sourced a framework
called slime um which basically is a
reinforcement learning uh architecture
for large scale RLVR or reinforcement
learning from verifiable rewards
[snorts] and it's also actually
compatible with uh existing tools like
cloud code or clin which is another
popular uh tool for coding with agents.
Um and here they actually plotted the
diff edit success rates between closed
source models in pink and open source
models in blue. As you can see, uh
performance is actually not that far
away. Like it's it's higher than 94%.
Um and so yeah, they actually provide
the whole documentation on how you can
easily replace an entropic model um by a
GLM model for example. Uh so yeah, some
people are of course making memes of
this like saying, "Thanks China for uh
unlimited cloth code for just $3 a
month." Um yeah, because these models
are actually a lot cheaper than uh than
these models from Entropic, for example.
And it's just a matter of replacing the
the API key. Um this was an other
interesting tweet I found from the
creator of Klein. Uh yeah, which is
another uh extension I think of VS Code.
Um so he says like if you plot the
performance gap between closed source
and open source like this gap is really
becoming really small. Uh so they're
improving fast and our users notice it
immediately because yeah they can do the
work at 10% of the cost. So that's quite
interesting uh to see and I think this
is like the latest uh model that is
currently uh making the waves uh which
is Kim K2 which is from a company called
Moonshot AI uh also Chinese uh again
they compare against the best uh closed
source models out there like GPD5 and
clotsson 4.5 again it's an open weights
model so there's no details on the
training data or the
Um but this is a really strong uh really
strong model which actually uh if you
look for example at the benchmark of
artificial artificial analysis they are
like in the third spot uh which is
pretty crazy to see again a huge
increase in the number of parameters.
This is a one trillion parameter model
with 32 billion of those active. Um, so
this is currently like the I would say
the state-of-the-art what what you can
find for free on hugging face
and this was another interesting tweet I
saw from Tim Dmers who is pretty known
for techniques like Q Laura and
quantization. So he says it's it's so
damn good. uh he's a very big cloud
fanboy, but he's now seriously
considering swapping it out for uh for
his model from from Moonshot, which is
quite interesting.
And yeah, Google released Gemini 3
yesterday, but weirdly they did not
compare against the best open- source
models. So someone from HackingFace just
added Kimmy into the table and as you
can see it even remains competitive
among these giant models uh despite
being freely available on Hugging Face
which is quite interesting to see.
Now yeah there's so much tooling that
HuggingFingace offers to get started
with open source. Um so you might wonder
how how do I get started with this?
Well, I would recommend going to
hugingface.com/learn
uh because there we do provide a huge
range of freely available courses. There
is an LLM course learning how to do
inference within LM, but also how to
fine-tune it on your custom data. Uh we
do have an agent course. We do have an
MCP course if you want to learn more
about the model context protocol. Um but
it's not just about LLM at phase. We
also do computer vision. We have
computer vision courses as well, OO
courses, deep reinforcement learning
courses. Uh LMS is just um one one of
the one of the domains of course that is
currently getting all of the attention.
So yeah, this was just a brief overview
of uh yeah the state of open source
coding models. I hope uh you learned
something and thanks for your attention.
[applause]
>> Thank you. Thank you very much Neils. Uh
it's great to see how much these open
source models are improving and giving
people actually an option to pick
whether they want to use open or close
based on performance. Any questions for
Neil's one at the back?
>> Um yeah, I was just wondering um what
the performance of like the GPT OSS
models are. They I didn't see them on
any of the benchmarks. I guess they're
not that great to the Chinese models.
Yeah, initially people weren't that
happy with GPT OSS, but then after like
let's say a month, people were actually
quite satisfied with them. Um, I don't
think you can like compare them to like
the best frontier models out there. For
that, you really need to have like a
trillion parameters as is currently the
case with this Kimmy model, but I think
they're still really great for like
ondevice purposes. Like for example,
Llama CPP is a popular framework uh for
running models on your laptop and uh
I've heard from the main uh contributor
of Llama CPP that GPT OSS is actually
one of the best models out there. So for
like ondevice use case, let's say
running on a phone or on laptop, they
are definitely uh good models, but I
wouldn't use them like for for coding
for example.
>> Yep, no worries.
>> Got 30 seconds. Got a quick question if
anyone has one.
If not, thank you very much. Neils,
please get up. Neils, thanks. [music]
[music]